A Guide to the Thomas Mott Shaw Drawings, approximately 1928-1933
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Thomas Mott Shaw Drawings, approximately 1928-1938
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 1945.4
34 items.
Shaw, Thomas Mott
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1945.
Biographical Information
Thomas Mott Shaw is best known as one of the founding partners and principal architects of the prominent Boston architectural firm Perry, Shaw and Hepburn which designed, planned and supervised the restoration of Williamsburg, Virginia. Born in 1878 in Newport, Rhode Island, Shaw received a Bachelor's degree from Harvard in 1900 and continued his education at the atelier of Jean-Louis Pascal at the École des Beaux-Arts in Paris from 1900 to 1905. He began his career in Boston, working for the architect Guy Lowell before opening his own business. Shaw served with the United States Army in France during World War I. Following the war, Shaw partnered with fellow architect Andrew H. Hepburn. William Graves Perry joined the firm in 1923 and it was this firm which was hired to restore Williamsburg to its 18th century appearance.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of thirty-four graphite and mixed media sketches drawn by architect Thomas Mott Shaw during the restoration of Williamsburg from the late 1920s through 1938, depicting various architectural exteriors and interiors of historic buildings in and around Colonial Williamsburg's Historic Area. In addition, two drawings depict African Americans involved in the work of the restoration.
Arrangement
Generally arranged alphabetically by drawing.
Index Terms
Persons:
Shaw, Thomas Mott
Subjects:
African Americans- -Virginia- -Williamsburg- -Pictorial views.; Historic buildings- -Virginia- -Williamsburg- -Pictorial views.
Contents List
- Ayscough Shop approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 45.5 x 31.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- John Blair House approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 43.5 x 29.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Botetourt Statue approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 24 x 45 cm. (Folder 1)
- Bracken Tenement 1928, 1 drawing; 21.5 x 28 cm. (Folder 1)
- Brick making (pug mill) approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 57 x 43 cm. (Folder 1)
- Brick making (clay molds approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 51 x 48 cm. (Folder 1)
- Capitol, south facade approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 29 x 43.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Coke-Garrett House, view looking northwest approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- William Finnie Quarters approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45 cm. (Folder 1)
- Gaol, north facade approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 47 x 33 cm. (Folder 1)
- Gaol and pillory approximately 1933, 1 drawing 31 x 45 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace, view looking northeast approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 43.5 x 29 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace entrance gate approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31.5 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace West Advance Building approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace and gardens, view looking southeast approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 45 x 31 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace garden with ballroom entrance approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 29 x 43.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace north facade through clairvoyée approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 32.5 x 47 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace gardens, bird's-eye view of boxwood parterre approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31.5 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace smokehouse and laundry approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45 cm. (Folder 1)
- Governor's Palace kitchen interior approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45 cm. (Folder 1)
- Grissell Hay kitchen approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 45.5 x 31 cm. (Folder 1)
- Ludwell-Paradise House stable approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45 cm. (Folder 1)
- Magazine, view looking west approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 43.5 x 29 cm. (Folder 1)
- Masonic Lodge approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 29.5 x 24.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Josias Moody and Ewing houses approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 43.5 x 29 cm. (Folder 1)
- John Orrell House approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 29 x 43.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Raleigh Tavern, view looking northeast approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 44.5 x 30.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Raleigh Tavern entrance approximately 1933, a drawing; 31 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- George Reid House approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 29 x 43.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- St. George Tucker House, south facade approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 47 x 33.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- St. George Tucker House, view looking east approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Williamsburg Inn, proposed 1938 addition approximately 1938, 1 drawing; 66 x 39.5 cm. (Folder 1)
- Wren Building, west facade approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 45.5 x 31 cm. (Folder 1)
- Wren Building, exterior entrance to Great Hall approximately 1933, 1 drawing; 31 x 45.5 cm. (Folder 1)